Finding Aid for Arthur Geoffrey Norman Papers 1947-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur Geoffrey Norman Papers 1947-1972
Norman, Arthur Geoffrey, 1905-
4 linear feet
Professor of botany at the University of Michigan, director of the Botanical Gardens, later vice-president for research. Correspondence, speeches, publications and reviews, and topical files relating to scientific interests, atomic energy, and the work of the Phoenix Project.
85539 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of these papers came from the University of Michigan Office of the Vice-President for Research (donor no. 5123 ) in 1975. A smaller amount of material came directly from Professor Norman (donor no. 6256 ) in 1978.
The collection is open for research.
Arthur Geoffrey Norman was born in Birmingham, England, November 26, 1905. He received a bachelor of science degree from the University of Birmingham in 1925. In 1928 he received a doctorate in biochemistry from the same institution. After serving for two years as a scientist at the Rothamsted Experimental Station, Norman came to the United States in 1930 as a Rockefeller Fellow at the University of Wisconsin. In 1932 he returned to England as the biochemist in charge of the biochemical section of the Rothamsted Experimental Station. In 1933 he received a second doctorate from the University of London.
In 1937 Norman left Rothamsted to become professor of soils at Iowa State University. During World War II he served in the US Army Chemical Corp., which led to his appointment in 1946 as biochemist and division chief of the Army's biological laboratories at Fort Detrick, Maryland. In 1952 Norman came to Ann Arbor, as professor of botany. Norman's interest in the University of Michigan was the result of a promise that he would head a plant nutrition project funded by a gift from the Ford Motor Company to the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project. In 1955 Norman added to this responsibility the directorship of the university's botanical gardens.
In 1964 Norman was appointed vice-president for research. He retired from this post in 1972, although he continued to serve in other university positions well after this date. A. Geoffrey Norman died in 1982.
A. Geoffrey Norman's papers date from 1947 to 1972 and measure four feet. They have been divided into three series, correspondence, speeches, publications and reviews, and topical. The correspondence series dates from 1951 to 1960. It is subdivided into two groups, general and personal. Each group is arranged chronologically. Speeches, publications and reviews are arranged alphabetically. They date from 1957 to 1972. The topical file is also arranged alphabetically, and dates from 1947 to 1965. It is particularly strong regarding the Ford Agricultural Plant Nutrition Project, which Norman headed when he first came to Michigan.
Subjects:
Botany.; Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; Norman, A. G. (Arthur Geoffrey), 1905-1982; Nuclear energy.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Botany.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Research.
- Correspondence
  - General
    - 1951-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956-June 1957 (Box 1)
    - July 1957-June 1958 (Box 1)
    - July 1958-June 1959 (Box 1)
    - July 1959-June 1960 (Box 1)
  - Personal
    - 1951-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955-June 1957 (Box 1)
    - July 1957-June 1958 (Box 1)
    - July 1958-June 1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960 (Box 1)
    - 1961 (Box 2)
    - 1962 (Box 2)
- Speeches, Publications and Reviews
  - American Astronautical Society September 16, 1968 (Box 2)
  - American Institute of Architects October 7, 1965 (Box 2)
  - American Society of Agronomy, Presidential Address November 20, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Argonne Radio-Botany Research Group 1959 (Box 2)
  - Army War College April 6, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Astrogeology Symposium March 22, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Auxin Activity undated (Box 2)
  - Biological Symposium May 1966 (Box 2)
  - Bir Seminar May 13, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Cellular Plastics in Construction, Conference on September 22, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Community College Counselor-Student Conference March 5, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Controlled Environment Facilities 1958 (Box 2)
  - Dedications of Buildings 1964-1969 (Box 2)
  - Dentistry, Research Perspectives in September 18-19, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Electrical Engineering Research Review October 7, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Engineering Society of Detroit May 17, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Foreign Students September 26, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Fort Detrick Banquet April 8, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes Research, Conference on May 5, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes Research Symposium October 28-29, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Highway Safety Research Institute: Prevention of Highway Injury April 19, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Highway Safety Research Institute: Information Conference November 16, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Hospital Financial Management, Conference on October 9, 1967 (Box 2)
  - IDD Housing Conference 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - International Conference on
    - Environmental Mercury Contamination September 30-October 1970 (Box 2)
    - Leukemia October 9, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Manufacturing Technology October 1967 (Box 2)
  - International Symposium on
    - Blood and Tissue Antigens September 17, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Eutrophication June 11, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Systematic Biology June 12-14, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Joint Automatic Control Conference of the American Automatic Control Council June 27, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Mechanical Engineering Centennial Convocation October 25, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Detroit Science Club February 27, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Planning Officials, Society of October 9, 1964 (Box 2)
  - National Biomedical Science Instrumentation Symposium May 19, 1969 (Box 2)
  - National Conference of Administration of Research
    - September 23, 1968 (Box 2)
    - September 23-26, 1970 (Box 2)
  - National Parks and Equivalent Reserve May 1966 (Box 2)
  - National Symposium on Quality Standards for Natural Waters July 1966 (Box 2)
  - Naval Research Reserve Units Seminar 1966 (Box 2)
  - Ohio State University 1960 (Box 2)
  - Oregon State College December 8, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Pharmacognosy, American Society for June 26, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Radioecology Symposium May 15, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Remote Sensing Symposium October 14, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Reviews of Manuscripts 1951-1964 (Box 2)
  - Role of the University in Research July 12-14, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Rotary Speech 1965 (Box 2)
  - Sesquicentennial Celebration 1967 (Box 2)
  - Sigma Xi February 10, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Soils Congress undated (Box 2)
  - Southern Illinois University May 11, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Speeches, Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - State Outdoors Recreation Planners Symposium May 6, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Structural Design of Asphalt Pavements, International Conference on August 7, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Symposium on Research in Agriculture February 24, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment May 17-21, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Symposium on Scientific Aspects of Pest Control January 31, 1966 (Box 3)
  - U-M "6411 Luncheon December 11, 1964 (Box 3)
  - URSI (International Scientific Radio Union) and IEEE (Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers) Antennas and Propagation October 17, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Water, Air and Noise Pollution November 21, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Reprints of writings 1926-1938, 3 volumes (Box 4)
- Topical File
  - Academic Press 1960-1965 (Box 3)
  - Advances in Agronomy by A. G. Norman (Box 3)
  - Agronomy Publications Committee 1955 (Box 3)
  - Air Pollution, Detroit Area 1953-1955 (Box 3)
  - American Society of Agronomy
    - Board of Directors 1956-1957 (Box 3)
    - Bylaw Amendment Petition 1956-1958 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee 1958 (Box 3)
    - Vice-President Nominating Committee 1959 (Box 3)
  - Andelot Project, University of Delaware 1960 (Box 3)
  - Biography (Box 3)
  - Cellulose and Cellulose Derivatives, 1951-1954 (Box 3)
  - Division of Biological Sciences, UM General Committee 1958-1960 (Box 3)
  - Ford Agricultural Plant Nutrition Project
    - General 1955-1964 (Box 3)
    - Committee Meetings 1951-1954 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - with Ford Motor Co. 1951-1954 (Box 3)
      - General 1952-1953 (Box 3)
    - Progress Reports 1954-1959 (Box 3)
    - Public Relations 1953 (Box 3)
  - Gordon Research Conferences 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Josiah Macy Foundation 1954-1956 (Box 3)
  - International Soils Congress 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Isotopes Conference 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Midwestern Plant Physiologists Meeting 1957 (Box 4)
  - National Research Council
    - Biomedical Committee on Civil Defense 1947, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Center of Prevention of Deterioration 1948-1955 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Plant and Crop Ecology 1952-1953 (Box 4)
    - Division of Biology and Agriculture 1952-1954 (Box 4)
    - Projects and Proposals Committee 1954-1956 (Box 4)
  - National Science Foundation
    - Controlled Environment Committee 1957 (Box 4)
    - Grant 917
      - General 1954-1958 (Box 4)
      - Budget 1955-1957 (Box 4)
      - Proposal 1956 (Box 4)
  - Northeastern Weed Control Conference, Committee on Terminology 1952 (Box 4)
  - Society of American Bacteriologists, Committee on Teaching 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - Soil Microbiology Institute
    - 1953-1954 (Box 4)
    - 1954 (Box 4)
  - Soil Sciences Organic Matter Round Table 1959 (Box 4)
  - Spencer Chemical Co. 1955-1958 (Box 4)
  - UMRI 1958-1960 (Box 4)
  - Willcox, O.W. 1958 (Box 4)